<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--
  Overall element for a Mathbook XML document; mandatory, always
  Including XInclude in order to segment the work into multiple chapter files,
  and perhaps ultimately individual section files.
-->
<!DOCTYPE doc>

<pretext xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <xi:include href="./bookinfo.xml" /> <!-- ISBN, website, other metadata -->

  <book xml:id="demo-exercises">
    <title>Dynamic Exercises</title>

    <xi:include href="./frontmatter.xml" />

    <chapter xml:id="chapter-motivation">
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <p>
        I have long been interested in interactive exercises for students learning mathematics.
        The promise is that students can try exercises that focus on particular skills or concepts
        and a computer will provide immediate feedback on whether they found an appropriate solution.
        When these problems are designed to allow for random variations with answer checkers that adapt to these variations,
        we have dynamic exercises.
      </p>
      <p>
        Dynamic exercises have a number of benefits.
        A single dynamic exercise creates a template for a large number of related problems.
        In a homework system, this allows a class of students to be assigned related problems that follow a common strategy
        while ensuring that students are individually solving problems with different details than (most of) those around them.
        For a single student, dynamic exercises allow a student to try new problems to reinforce earlier practice.
        The computer might be able to recognize submitted answers that result from common mistakes or misconceptions
        and provide feedback that can guide the student to correct their error.
      </p>
      <p>
        Dynamic exercises also have some challenges.
        For an author, there is the complication of writing a generalization of an exercise.
        Key aspects of the problem that allow mutation introduce parameters for randomization.
        The author then needs to ensure that different random versions of the problem have comparable complexity and methods of solution.
        An answer and solution that incorporates the variability is also necessary.
      </p>
      <p>
        Online homework systems are one way that the idea of dynamic exercises is realized.
        WeBWorK is one example of a system that allows authors to create custom problems 
        as well as to provide logic to evaluate student responses.
        Other learning systems implement similar models.
        These different systems have their own approaches for how an author defines and writes their exercises.
      </p>
      <p>
        PreTeXt-authored books now allow WeBWorK exercises to be embedded within the text.
        Once such a problem is activated, a student can anonymously submit a response to a question
        and a remote server can evaluate their submission and provide appropriate feedback.
        I am exploring the possibility and practicality of generalizing the inclusion of dynamic exercises
        where an author can define the logic and structure of the exercise 
        rather than provide code specific to a particular system like WeBWorK.
      </p>
      <assemblage>
        <title>Anticipated Objectives</title>
        <p>
          <ul>
            <li>An XML-based definition of an exercise can allow for transcoding to different systems, e.g. WeBWorK, WebAssign, or other systems.</li>
            <li>An author can focus on the structure and logic of a dynamic exercise rather than the syntax and language-specific implementations.</li>
            <li>A Javascript evaluation engine could create a server-free implementation of problems reducing the reliance of a text on 3rd party servers.</li>
          </ul>
        </p>
      </assemblage>
      <p>
        WeBWorK allows incredible flexibility in authoring questions.
        This XML-based approach to defining problems is not intended to support that full flexibility.
        Part of the development challenge will be to identify a core set of features that make sense.
      </p>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="chapter-markup">
      <title>Markup</title>
      <section xml:id="section-markup-exercise">
        <title>Overview of Exercise Markup</title>
        <p>
          As much as possible, the markup should follow PreTeXt standards.
          One goal is that any user-facing content on a web-page should match the style of other elements generated by PreTeXt.
          Problems transcoded to WeBWorK should match how similar problems defined in PreTeXt using <tag>pg</tag> elements are created.
          Consequently, tags supported for standard exercises should be supported natively as much as possible in dynamic exercises.
        </p>
        <remark>
          <p>
            This is very much a draft proposal for markup.
            Ideas for improvement and implementation warnings are welcome.
          </p>
        </remark>
        <p>
          My initial idea is that an <tag>exercise</tag> element could have an attribute <c>@dynamic='yes'</c> to indicate that the exercise involves dynamic processing.
          The PreTeXt processing of such elements would require a comparable strategy for embedding a WeBWorK exercise.
          This would include generating the corresponding <c>pg</c> files and having a WeBWorK server process the files so that they could be pulled back into the PreTeXt document for final processing.
          A potential Javascript implementation would need to generate appropriate resources for dynamically inserting the problems into HTML.
        </p>
        <p>
          The overall structure of an exercise is proposed to have the following structure.
          There are two XML blocks that are specific to a dynamic exercise, <c>setup</c> and <c>evaluation</c>.
          The other blocks are intended to match PreTeXt standard usage.
          An <c>answer</c> block perhaps does not make sense.
          The other standard elements will be formatted as usual, with some additional tags to
          specify where items such as values and expressions are inserted.
        </p>
        <listing>
          <pre><![CDATA[ 
            <exercise xml:id='my-id' @dynamic='yes'>
              <setup> <!-- Specify the dynamic problem randomization elements -->
                ...
              </setup>
              <statement> <!-- Usual PreTeXt with elements to include dynamic expressions -->
                ...
              </statement>
              <evaluation> <!-- Specify the dynamic problem evaluation and feedback -->
                ...
              </evaluation>
              <solution> <!-- Usual PreTeXt with elements to include dynamic expressions -->
                ...
              </solution>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
          </pre>
          <caption>Overall XML structure of a dynamic exercise.</caption>
        </listing>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="section-markup-setup">
        <title>Setup and Randomization</title>
        <p>
          The <c>setup</c> block defines all of the dynamically generated mathematical objects.
          It also specifies particular constraints on any variables in the system.
          The tag has an attribute <c>seed</c> which is used to provide a default seed for the initial state of the problem.
          To support WeBWorK's approach, this should be set equal to a string containing a positive integer.
          The block consists of a sequence of instruction elements.
        </p>
        <p>
          Instruction elements can define parameters, variables, and expression terms.
          Parameters can be generated randomly or calculated in terms of previously defined parameters.
          Expression terms can be computed in terms of previously defined parameters or expressions using the defined variables.
          All of these elements have <c>@name</c> attribute.
          Parameter and expression names should start with a letter and can contain letters A-Za-z, digits 0-9, and the underscore.
          I have to check whether variable names have the same flexibility, but they might only allow letters.
        </p>
        <paragraphs xml:id="mustache-substitution">
          <title>Mustache Substitution</title>
          <p>
            Implementations of dynamic exercises will reference the parameter and expression names in different ways.
            For example, WeBWorK and WebAssign both use Perl syntax and so the names will be transcoded with a dollar sign $ before the name.
            Other implementations will just use the names directly.
            To retain a simple substitution schema when <em>defining</em> a value or an expression, we adopt <term>mustache substitution</term>.
            This means that the name of the parameter or expression needs to be surrounded by double curly braces.
            Variables themselves are not enclosed by braces.
            For example, if we had previously defined a parameter <c>c</c> and wanted to introduce an expression <m>cx+3</m>,
            the mustache-substitution expression would be written <c>{{c}}*x+3</c>.
          </p>
          <p>
            When referring to parameters or expressions for display in PreTeXt content or to refer to expressions as objects for evaluation (as in when checking answers), we instead use XML tags and use the <c>#var</c> element
            with <c>@name="expression-name"</c> to match.
          </p>
        </paragraphs>
        <p>
          <dl>
            <li xml:id="tag-de-parameter"><title>de-parameter</title>
              <p>Used to define a numeric value, generated either randomly or statically.</p>
              <p>
                Attributes:
                <dl>
                  <li><title>@name</title>
                    <p>Name starts with letter and can contain A-Za-z, 0-9 and underscore.</p>
                  </li>
                  <li><title>@random</title>
                    <p>Value is a string specifying how the value is randomly assigned.</p>
                    <p><c>random='discrete'</c> means the value will be chosen from an finite sequence of equally spaced values. Uses the additional attributes <c>@min</c>, <c>@max</c>, <c>@by</c>, and <c>@nonzero</c>.</p>
                    <p><c>random='uniform'</c> means the value will be chosen uniformly between a minimum and maximum value. Uses the additional attributes <c>@min</c> and <c>@max</c>.</p>
                    <p>Need to think about markup for choosing one or more values from an arbitrary list.</p>
                  </li>
                  <li><title>@min</title>
                    <p>Value is a number for the minimum of either discrete or uniform random values. Default: <c>min="0"</c></p>
                  </li>
                  <li><title>@max</title>
                    <p>Value is a number for the maximum of either discrete or uniform random values. Default: <c>max="1"</c>. For the discrete sequence, the maximum is technically just an upper bound. Sequence values above <c>@max</c> are not selected</p>
                  </li>
                  <li><title>@by</title>
                    <p>Value is a number for the step size increment of a discrete sequence. Default: <c>by="1"</c></p>
                  </li>
                  <li><title>@nonzero</title>
                    <p>Value is <q>yes</q> or <q>no</q>, to indicate for a discrete random choice whether the value of zero should always be excluded. Default: <c>nonzero="no"</c></p>
                  </li>
                </dl>
              </p>
              <p>
                Content: 
                When the parameter is not randomly assigned, the content of the element is used to define the value of the parameter. 
                The parameter can be calculated in terms of previously defined parameters using <xref ref="mustache-substitution" text="custom">mustache substitution</xref>. 
                Variables and names of expressions can not be used.
                For randomly generated values, the content is empty.
              </p>
            </li>
            <li xml:id="tag-de-variable"><title>de-variable</title>
              <p>Define a symbol that will be treated as a variable. The default variable of <m>x</m> is not required to be defined.</p>
              <p>
                I propose that there is no content and the name of the variable is defined with the attribute <c>@name</c>.
                I am wondering if child elements might be included to define context information about the domain where the variable is defined and values where the variable is evaluated when comparing expressions.
              </p>
              <p>
                WeBWorK distinguishes variables as being real- or complex-valued. I do not believe WebAssign allows for complex-variable expressions. Should we have an attribute for this?
              </p>
              <p>
                An alternative implementation would be to have a tag <c>de-variables</c> and then have the content be a list of the variables that are used. We would need to specify the delimiter (space or comma default?).
              </p>
            </li>
            <li xml:id="tag-de-term"><title>de-term</title>
              <p>Used to define an expression capable of being used in comparisons for evaluation.</p>
              <p>
                In my mind, I am thinking of this like a MathObject formula in WeBWorK or as an expression that is going to appear inside of a problem statement or solution. 
                WeBWorK MathObjects and my proposed Javascript implementation allow complex manipulation of expressions, including substitution, evaluation, and differentiation. 
                WebAssign, on the other hand, seems to think of expressions as static formulas.
                My proposed markup is intended to allow for manipulation.
                A future conversion to WebAssign would either be more complex (simple substitution should be possible using Perl functions) or require warning about unsupported features.
              </p>
              <p>
                Attributes:
                <dl>
                  <li><title>@name</title>
                    <p>Name starts with letter and can contain A-Za-z, 0-9 and underscore.</p>
                  </li>
                  <li><title>@context</title>
                    <p>Value is a string specifying how the expression is defined.</p>
                    <p><c>context='formula'</c> means the content is a mustache-substitution formula.</p>
                    <p><c>context='substitution'</c> means the formula is defined by a variable substitution from another formula. The content contains child elements: <c>#start</c> containing either a <c>de-term</c> defining the initial expression or <c>#var</c> matching a previously-defined expression; <c>#match</c> containing the variable being replaced; and <c>#replace</c> containing another expression defined by <c>#de-term</c> or <c>#var</c>.</p>
                    <p>
                      I'm wondering about whether it would make more sense for <c>#start</c> and <c>#replace</c> to have a name attribute to match previous formulas and content only if needing to define on the spot, and similarly for <c>#match</c> to only have a name matching the variable and no content.
                    </p>
                    <p>I can see adding contexts for the derivative of a previously-defined expression. I can also see this allowing non-formula contexts as well, similar to other MathObject contexts (intervals, sets, lists).</p>
                  </li>
                </dl>
              </p>
            </li>
          </dl>
        </p>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="section-markup-evaluation">
        <title>Evaluation and Feedback</title>
        <p>
          In the content of the exercise, specifically in the <c>statement</c> element and its content, 
          the author should insert <c>fillin</c> elements for where answers will be entered for evaluation.
          Each <c>#fillin</c> should have a <c>@submit</c> attribute that will give a name used for matching evaluation rules to the specific student response.
          It should also have a <c>@correct</c> attribute that gives the name of a <c>#de-term</c> formula element that represents a possible correct answer.
          It also has an optional attribute <c>@width</c> that specifies how large the answer blank should be.
          The <c>evaluation</c> block of XML provides the necessary information for how to determine whether student answers are correct.
          It also is responsible for describing any special feedback that is provided to the student, 
          such as answer hints specific to the submitted student response.
        </p>
        <p>
          The <c>evaluation</c> block contains <c>evaluate</c> elements. Each <c>evaluate</c> element is associated with a particular answer blank based on matching <c>@submit</c> attributes. Tests within this element are specific to that submission response and any provided feedback will be attached to that submission. In the event that submission responses are coupled and correctness can only be determined by referencing one another, the <c>evaluation</c> element needs to have an attribute <c>@answers-coupled="yes"</c>. Rules for checking answers can then refer to student submissions from other answer blanks. It is also possible to create a single answer checker for all answer blanks by including an <c>evaluate</c> element with the attribute <c>@all="yes"</c>, in which case all other <c>evaluate</c> elements are only used for feedback and not determining correctness.
        </p>
        <listing xml:id="listing-evaluation-block-single">
          <pre><![CDATA[ 
            <evaluation>
              <evaluate submit="answerBlank1">  <!-- Block to provide feedback for matching fillin -->
                ...
              </evaluate>
              <evaluate submit="answerBlank2">  <!-- Block to provide feedback for matching fillin -->
                ...
              </evaluate>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
          </pre>
          <caption>XML structure of the evaluation block for independent answer blanks.</caption>
        </listing>
        <listing xml:id="listing-evaluation-block-mixed">
          <pre><![CDATA[ 
            <evaluation answers-coupled="yes">
              <evaluate all="yes">  <!-- Block to evaluate entire exercise at once -->
                ...
              </evaluate>
              <evaluate submit="answerBlank1">  <!-- Block to provide limited feedback for matching fillin -->
                ...
              </evaluate>
              <evaluate submit="answerBlank2">  <!-- Block to provide limited feedback for matching fillin -->
                ...
              </evaluate>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
          </pre>
          <caption>XML structure of the evaluation block for independent answer blanks.</caption>
        </listing>
        <p>
          Each <c>evaluate</c> element consists of a sequence of <c>test</c> elements. A <c>test</c> element with <c>@correct="yes"</c> indicates that this test is used to determine the correctness of the submission associated with the parent <c>evaluate</c> element. Any other <c>test</c> elements are used to provide feedback. If no <c>test</c> element has <c>@correct="yes"</c>, then the default test is to do a direct comparison with the formula assigned by the <c>@correct</c> attribute of the associated <c>#fillin</c>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Each <c>test</c> element consists of the logical test and a <c>feedback</c> element giving the text response when the logical test results in a true value.
          The logical test can consist of a formula object specified by either <c>var</c> or <c>de-term</c> elements, in which case truth is determined by testing if the student answer matches the given formula object.
          The logical test can also compare any two formula elements using an <c>#equal</c> logical test element, where one or both of the formula elements were constructed using the student responses.
          Or the logical test can be a composite logical tests using Boolean operators <c>#and</c>, <c>#or</c>, or <c>#not</c>, with child elements containing additional logical tests.
          Because requiring multiple tests to be true is common, the root test is presumed to be like <c>#and</c> when there are multiple logical tests as children of the <c>test</c> element.
        </p>
        <listing xml:id="listing-evaluate-block-simple-test">
          <pre><![CDATA[ 
              <evaluate submit="answerBlank1">
                <test correct="yes">
                  <var name="expression1"/>
                </test>
                <test>
                  <var name="expression2"/>
                  <feedback>custom response</feedback>
                </test>
              </evaluate>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
          </pre>
          <caption>XML structure of the evaluate block marking correct if <c>answerBlank1</c> and <c>expression1</c> match and giving <q>custom response</q> as feedback if it matches <c>expression2</c>.</caption>
        </listing>
        <listing xml:id="listing-evaluate-block-coupled-test">
          <pre><![CDATA[ 
              <evaluate all="yes">
                <test correct="yes">
                  <equal>
                    <var name="expression1" />
                    <var name="answerBlank1" />
                  </equal>
                  <equal>
                    <var name="expression2" />
                    <var name="answerBlank2" />
                  </equal>
                </test>
              </evaluate>
            </exercise>
            ]]>
          </pre>
          <caption>XML structure of the evaluate block marking all correct (requires <c>@answers-coupled="yes"</c>). There is an implicit <c>#and</c> surrounding the two <c>equal</c> elements.</caption>
        </listing>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="chapter-demonstration">
      <title>Demonstration</title>
      <section xml:id="section-demonstration-usage">
        <title>Usage</title>
        <p>
          I have worked up a prototype parser of XML markup to PGML WeBWorK problems.
          In my <c>dynamic-examples</c> branch of the PreTeXt <c>mathbook</c> project,
          I have added a file <c>dynamicexercise.xsl</c>.
          (It is also included in this project, but not in the assumed PreTeXt path.)
          This creates a <c>.pg</c> file for each <c>exercise</c> element in the project that has the attribute <c>@dynamic="yes"</c>.
        </p>
        <pre>
          > cd ::project-directory::
          > mkdir pg; cd pg
          > xsltproc --xinclude ::pretext-path::/xsl/dynamicexercise.xsl ::project-root-xml::
        </pre>
        <p>
          This project has demonstration exercises.
          I have not linked the resulting WeBWorK output as I do not have access to a server and have not gone through the process yet.
          However, the next sections in this chapter provide listings.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="section-markup-examples">
        <title>Examples of Markup</title>

        <p>
          The first example is for solving a linear equation of the form <m>mx+b=0</m>.
          The parameters <m>m</m> and <m>b</m> are created randomly.
        </p>

        <listing>
          <pre>
            <xi:include href="exercise-solve-equation.xml" parse="text" />
          </pre>
          <caption><c>exercise-solve-equation.xml</c></caption>
        </listing>
        <listing>
          <pre>
            <xi:include href="../pg/solve-equation.pg" parse="text" />
          </pre>
          <caption><c>solve-equation.pg</c></caption>
        </listing>

        <p>
          A second example is calculating derivatives of a simple polynomial of the form <m>f(x)=ax^n+b</m>.
          The parameters <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>n</m> are created randomly.
        </p>

        <listing>
          <pre>
            <xi:include href="exercise-find-derivatives.xml" parse="text" />
          </pre>
          <caption><c>exercise-solve-equation.xml</c></caption>
        </listing>
        <listing>
          <pre>
            <xi:include href="../pg/find-derivatives.pg" parse="text" />
          </pre>
          <caption><c>solve-equation.pg</c></caption>
        </listing>

        <p>
          A third example illustrates coupled answers and asks to find two functions
          <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> so that <m>f(g(x))</m> equals a given function.
        </p>

        <listing>
          <pre>
            <xi:include href="exercise-find-derivatives.xml" parse="text" />
          </pre>
          <caption><c>exercise-solve-equation.xml</c></caption>
        </listing>
        <listing>
          <pre>
            <xi:include href="../pg/find-derivatives.pg" parse="text" />
          </pre>
          <caption><c>solve-equation.pg</c></caption>
        </listing>
      </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter xml:id="live-exercises">
      <title>Live Exercises</title>
      <p>
        This is where the live WeBWorK problems would go and where they are coded into the project.
        PreTeXt currently doesn't know what to do with the <c>var</c> elements, so they don't appear properly.
      </p>
      <exercises>
        <xi:include href="./exercise-solve-equation.xml" />
        <xi:include href="./exercise-find-derivatives.xml" />
        <xi:include href="./exercise-decompose-function.xml" />
      </exercises>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</pretext>
